Transcriber: Göksu Doğan
Reviewer: Vaia Katsarou
I first found my love of engineering
and automotive technology
a mere six miles down the road.
With my engineering degree
I designed steering columns,
I launched seeding programs,
I went back to school again
and became a lawyer,
where now I work with automotive companies
to get technology into the market.
It's a fantastic opportunity.
But what really set me aflame
was driverless cars.
The notion of these sensors
and these systems, the AI,
just fascinating technology.
But what, really, drew me
was the vision of a more
perfect driving future,
inclusion for the disabled,
for the elderly,
and for those underserved communities.
To me that was important.
And what cemented this
was my very first speaking gig
on autonomous vehicles.
Now, granted, I was there
speaking about what happens
when these car crashes happen
and who’s to blame.
And everybody wanted to know
who do you blame.
But there were people at that conference
that, really, were doing amazing work.
I met the delegation
from the State of Nevada,
and they told me about Sam Schmidt,
a race car driver, who was rendered
paralyzed following an accident.
It was Sam's goal to get back behind
the proverbial wheel of a vehicle again,
and they wanted
that inclusive future for him.
In 2016, Sam was blessed to be one
of the first people in the country
with a license to ride.
Now, he did have his opportunity
and he’s there,
but what’s happened to technology since.
The cars keep getting smarter,
I mean, they’re computers on wheels,
but we still have challenges.
Let's take a look at an example.
The Tesla full self drive.
Now, yes, Tesla full self drive
is not an automated vehicle,
not, not really.
But let’s look at how it works
because that’s really critical
to this whole operation of AVs.
Drivers collect all of this information,
Tesla synthesizes it,
they code it and put it back
into the AI engine,
and the car learns to drive and improves.
But wait a minute.
What is your average
Tesla driver look like?
Well, demographics tell us they have,
at least, an income of $150,000,
75% of them are male,
70% of them don’t have children at home,
and over 80% are white.
Now, LendingTree came out
with some recent statistics
that show us that there are
a couple of other things
that we may want to think about.
According to LendingTree,
they are the second most likely
to have vehicle incidents
and the most likely to have
vehicle crashes per thousand vehicles.
Now, not to be too harsh on Tesla,
there are shortcomings in the data sets
and the collection
of other automakers as well.
And when you have shortcomings,
when you have limited data sets,
unfortunate situations happen.
In 2019, Georgia Tech conducted
a seminal study on these vision systems
and how they detect pedestrians.
Georgia Tech found
that there was, nearly, a 10% difference
in the ability of these systems to detect
dark skinned people
versus light skinned people.
In 2023, this study was redone
by King’s College in London.
Now, what King's College
found is things have improved.
7% difference, but King’s College,
also, found other issues.
These systems are 20% more likely
to detect adults
when compared to children.
Clearly, to get good AV systems
on the road,
we need an inclusive design.
And by inclusive design,
I think of my friends
in the privacy realm,
they wanted to bring privacy to us
throughout the chain,
they created privacy by design.
So privacy wasn't an afterthought.
To have an inclusive mobility,
we need inclusion by design,
not as an afterthought.
So, how do we get there?
I’ll give you some tenets
of inclusion by design in AI,
with three stories.
I’m going to talk about
a wheelchair and a duck,
honking horns and a taco truck.
So, let’s start in 2016
with the wheelchair and the duck.
Google had this vehicle
and it was testing around the town,
and what it found was
a wheelchair and a duck.
They called it the renegade granny
on an electric vehicle
chasing ducks around.
What was fantastic is the vehicle stopped.
It did exactly what it was supposed to do.
It recognized that the electric wheelchair
had a person on it,
and that the duck was important as well.
So it was able to identify all people.
Expanding upon that, we need systems,
AI, data sets that can identify all people
regardless of their gender,
their age, or their race.
So let's fast forward
to just a few weeks ago,
Waymo driverless vehicles
in San Francisco.
When a driverless vehicle is done,
when a Waymo is done,
it kind of congregates in a parking lot,
and really it’s an elegant dance
if you see the videos.
The problem is, when they do this dance,
they get really close to each other,
and they start to honk all night long,
really affecting
those neighborhood communities,
those apartment buildings that are really
adjacent to that parking lot.
Look at the bigger picture.
That was an unintended consequence.
We need to look at the communities
that are impacted.
Even if the vision system
isn’t seeing them,
we need to include the larger scale
and the larger scope.
Let's stay in San Francisco
and rewind back to 2017.
The taco truck.
A vehicle detected a taco truck
and it stopped.
I mean, come on, who wouldn’t want
to stop for a taco truck?
The problem was,
it didn't start back up again.
It saw the pedestrians
going back and forth,
and it thought I’ve got to stop,
I don’t know what to do.
The safety driver took control
and escorted the vehicle away.
Inclusion by design necessitates,
thinking about location and where we’re at
Τhe communities that surround them,
and the interactions,
whether it’s suburban or urban.
So we've got
inclusion by design.
We have identify all people.
We have look at the bigger picture,
and we have think about location.
So, with inclusion by design,
and remembering the story
of the wheelchair and the duck,
honking cars and the taco truck
will be able to move towards
that total inclusion by design.
It’s something we need to teach
in our engineering schools.
It's something that needs to be considered
by our standards bodies.
It's something that the regulators
need to start thinking,
so,we can, truly, move forward
to that vision of an inclusive mobility.
(Applause)